so this video isn't going to do very
well because I don't actually think that
many people care about clo but if you
clicked on this video I'm going to
ignore everything that I've learned
about making videos to optimize audience
retention and reward you by blowing your
mind with some serious science across 10
studies that I analyzed for this video
we're going to go on a journey you and
me yes it's going to be complex no it's
not going to be easily digestible and I
don't give a damn let's PhD this and
I'll try my best to walk you through the
complexities if you accidentally clicked
on this video clo is a protein secreted
by your cells that has some fascinating
science indicating it packs a serious
punch in protecting your brain from
developing dementia especially
Alzheimer's in fact this includes the
devastating Apo E4 versions of
Alzheimer's which is especially
intriguing check this out in this study
that I just referenced researchers
recruited people with a high likelihood
of developing Alzheimer's because they
have one gene of apoe4 which is a
heavily implicated Gene in developing
Alzheimer's they then split these people
into two groups one group had normal clo
expression meaning they produced normal
amounts of clo protein the other group
had a specific clth mutation meaning
they also have the clog Gene that allows
them to produce this protein but they
have a slight change in the gene
structure a mutation that increases the
amount of clo that they produce so then
what did the researchers discover after
doing brain scans on these Alzheimer's
prone individuals well they had several
measurements but I'll highlight one of
the most telling here we're looking at
cerebros spinal fluid beta ameloid
protein to orient you this is a key
protein implicated in Alzheimer's
disease the researchers are looking at
the cerebros spinal fluid the liquid
outside of your brain cells to determine
if the cells are able to release a beta
ameloid protein effectively the blue
bars represent people without this
genetic Alzheimer's risk because they do
not have copies of apoe4 Gene that we
mentioned ear
the red bars are the people with this
apoe4 Gene with the klvs snc being
people with a normal clog Gene and the
kls are the ones with this mutation in
one of their clog genes leading to
assumed greater clo expression as we can
see in the middle bars those with the
apoe4 gene yet no cloog gene mutation
have reduced cerebros spinal fluid beta
ameloid levels this would suggest that
these people are retaining more beta
ameloid in their cells not a good thing
in addition those with the cloom
mutation experience more beta amid in
their cerebros spinal fluid indicating
that they are releasing it from the
cells to be clear some of this is
speculation but other data from this
study does indicate more beta amid
protein inside the brain when the clo
mutation is not present this is also
corroborated in this study okay so we
know something is happening but what
about long-term data do people with this
mutation and assumed higher cloo levels
actually have a brain protected effect
well let's return to this study that I
briefly popped up and again we're
looking at two groups of people with the
same apoe4 gene one group without this
assumed protective clo of mutation and
one group with the clo of mutation
this time however we're not looking at
beta ID protein although they did that
too but we're looking at the incidence
of Alzheimer's disease and Mild
cognitive impairment across decades we
see that data here with the dark line
being those without the cloth of
mutation and the yellow line being the
people with the
mutation then the vertical axis is the
incidence of Alzheimer's or MCI mild
cognitive impairment so the higher the
lines go the worse clearly there is a
separation between the two groups there
is a substantial reduction in cognitive
impairment risk in people with this clo
mutation to be fair these are not
adjusted analyses so it's possible there
is some confounding variable that is the
true explanation but considering what
we've already seen about CL though
there's at least a good chance that this
is due to clo although not
infallible okay
with this uncertainty could we find more
direct ways to see if clo is directing
these effects also what if I told you it
uh wasn't exactly clo directly causing
these effects and can we just administer
clo well let's go another layer deeper
for that we can lean on this study where
in researchers injected clo into monkeys
and measured their cognitive per
performance we see the cognitive test
here we have a baseline so before
injection then the control condition
known as a vehicle so that's the non-cl
injection and then the clo injection the
vertical axis is the performance on the
cognitive task the higher the better
clearly the cloo condition improved
relative to the other two to be clear
these are not Alzheimer's Afflicted
monkeys and still there is a benefit to
the brain but other studies like this
want to investigate the effect in other
animal models and confirm the
Alzheimer's effects including
Alzheimer's specific mechanisms which I
can cover in the future for now we
understand that clo has likely a direct
cognitive benefit but I did tease that
this might be a bit misunderstood here's
why usually when we inject A protein
that protein binds or interacts in some
way with the cells that changes their
behavior
however we know that clo does not cross
the blood brain barrier so it never
actually interacts with the brain at
least not from the rest of the body so
if it's separated from the brain how is
it enacting these effects remember the
monkeys are not injected in the brain
but just like any other injection so why
did they experience benefit well through
super cool mechanisms so since this
video is already going to tank let's go
another layer deeper and maybe we can
drum up some complaints about how this
is too complicated in the comments if we
pop open this uh influential study in
this study the researchers again
injected clo into animals and showed
again an improvement in cognitive
ability think Limitless but for mice
these mice started beating the
researchers in chess and seduce their
wives with their Superior intellect
anyway they also analyzed what other
molecules are highly expressed after
injection of clo and they discovered
that multiple molecules related to
platelets were highly expressed
platelets are the cell fragments that
circulate in your blood and when
activated begin the clotting Cascade
meaning that they Clump together to
create clots that without context sounds
scary but activating platelets can mean
many things and in this case Clos seems
to directly activate platelets in the
blood indicated here here we're seeing
researchers measure blood platelet
Factor 4 so pf4 a marker of platelet
activation with vehicle or control
injection and with clo injection the clo
injection leads to a rise in platelet
Factor 4 indicating a likely activation
of the platelets in the body however
when the researchers use a platelet
activation inhibitor on the right there
there is no increase in PL Factor 4 in
addition when taking absolutely gorgeous
brain slices on the right side we see
the researchers are using different
color markers to identify different
sections of the brain the red one is the
one indicating the platet factor 4 or
clo or vehicle so in both clo and
vehicle we see only a background of red
however we see large amounts of platelet
Factor 4 pf4 this confirms that clo
likely doesn't cross the bloodb brain
barrier and pf4 does which is how clo at
least provides some of its effects
in the image on the left which I added
simply because it's well a beautiful
image the orange areas are the pf4 tack
anyway there's a lot more to this study
like the fact that clo benefits old and
young mice and the effect of pf4 has on
cognitive ability but let's discuss how
we can apply this information because I
know that's what many want so that's a
fair ask well look we haven't gotten to
the point where we're injecting people
with clo but I would not be surprised if
that's coming that said that doesn't
mean there isn't something else that you
could do to improve clo levels in fact
exercise increases clo levels and I
won't bog you down with some of the
details on this specific analysis
although there are some minor errors in
it the results are likely still sound
namely exercise raises blood clo levels
we see that here if the Black Diamond
there moves to the right it indicates
exercise increases cloo levels and I
know this number known as Hedges G might
not mean anything to you but it
signifies the effect is pretty big too
let's get into the type of exercise to
before we do that if you're a physionic
Insider I'll be covering how to identify
the clog Gene to identify if you have
the protective mutation or not in
addition I'll be covering some more
details on increasing cloo through
exercise like is there an upper
threshold is it raised more in some
people than others if you're interested
in that plus the podcast premium videos
summaries research reviews and more be
sure to join the link is in the
description I would love to have you
aboard The physionic Insider train okay
now what type of exercise well that same
analysis broke studies up by the type of
exercise from endurance longdistance
exercise to resistance training overall
resistance training had more robust
evidence pointing towards a clo raising
role however endurance exercise also
raise clo levels either way the current
evidence points in favor of resistance
training as being superior but a direct
comparison between the two is necessary
to be sure now better educated and well
equipped you now have a better
understanding of how clo protects your
brain and a natural way to enhance it at
least until science delivers us some
Alternatives we can never sleep on
exercise thanks for sticking out with me
and check out this next video for more
on brain health
[Music]
[Applause]